in the last episode we exported an mvr file from
wysiwyg lighting design software from cast-soft
this time i'll show you the easy way to set up
your GrandMA3 layout to reflect what's in your
GrandMA3 3D window GrandMA3 has a great and simple
tool that's going to help you make your setup
based on your fixtures position in the 3d universe
so if you want to be a better and faster GrandMA3
programmer this tutorial is definitely for you
if you haven't watched the last episode i'll link
it in the corner right now but you don't have
to use that setup you can follow along if you
made your own 3d setup but you must have some
fixtures ready in your GrandMA3 3d window for
this technique to work in the description below
i've shared a onedrive link where you can download
this GrandMA3 show file feel free to use it for
this tutorial if you don't have something of your
own setup right now if you go into the folder
it's the episode 18 folder so let's get into it
as you might remember from the last tutorial
we imported this mvr file as you can see right
here and this consists of a lot of fixtures and
building a layout file from all these fixtures
in the right position is going to take you a long
time and that's why GrandMA3 has a really really
great tool which is going to help you in that
in that regard but the first thing here we look
at it in 3d and then we have our cameras up here
which determines from which angle we are watching
it right now so if i press the front it's going to
show us the front it's going to show us front and
left left back lift back and so on and so forth
and this is this is something that's going to help
us in a minute when we build our layout but before
we build our layout i you have to build a layout
view which i've done here i have some groups i
have some playbacks here which we're going to
need later i have some macros for easy access
instead of writing everything out in the command
line i have my sequences ready down here i can
see what's in the sequence when i store some
and i have my fixture sheet here so there's a few
different ways you can make a group first of all
you can of course just type the numbers you can
type fixture one through and the last one in in
that chain of the fixtures and another thing
is you can go over here and you can simply
drag drag the cursor down until you you select
all the fixtures in a certain fixture type
this time i'm going to do it with all our two
lights right now and it's a little bit difficult
because it reacts really fast sometimes but i
think i've put in 175 two lights we have marked
them out now we can simply say store and put
them into a group up here we label the group
all two lights like this and then i'm going to
speed up the video and do exactly the same thing
for the other moving lines and the other fixtures
in our 3d space once you've stored everything into
its own group it's much easier to work with
not that we have to do that we could actually
basically just select all fixtures and put them
into the view but this way we have a little bit
more control when we need to work with them later
but as we have done we have a build our layout
right here we just need to scale this a little bit
down and we need our layout pool in here as well
and it's over here somewhere and we're going to
need that in a minute let's just store this into
our current layout view right here there we go so
clear this now we go we need our two lights our
atomics our spiders mega points auras and vipers
and we need to assign them into this layout view
so we have just selected all of them and we simply
say assign and we put them in here and as you can
see this is all our fixtures but they are just
in one big long line right now and we can't use
that for anything really so here comes the cool
part you can go up into your setup menu here
with everything selected you can go into your
position down here and you can click it and say
arrangement you can right click this one and say
camera and if you remember before we used we could
we switch around the cameras in 3d window so here
in the camera setting you can simply right click
or left click and and go up and say okay from
which angle do i need to set this up right now
if you do it from the front view like this one
it's gonna be basically set up the layout of
if you see it from the front i love to see it from
the top this is the way i like to work with it
so i select the top view and then we go down
into our settings down here and we say apply
and now we actually set up everything as we're
supposed to we can mark everything here and we can
take our little move tool here and we can move it
into the center and now we very very quickly built
a layout for our setup but as you can see this
layout is practically useless because everything
is positioned on top of each other so we need
to separate this out the easiest way we can
so we have all our fixtures stored in this first
one up here so when we press that that's the
the view with all our fixtures in it so let's
just copy this one and move it down here and
we can relabel this to all atomics for instance
like this and then we can go in and select it
and it looks exactly the same because it's a
copy of course so we say edit and then we find
everything in here which is not an atomic and we
simply delete it so we start up here with all the
two lights we select them and we delete them we
go below the atomics and we find all the spiiders
and all the way down and we delete that and then
we close this one down and then we suddenly only
have all our atomics in our view but it's still
a little clunky because we are looking from the
the top and you can see they are a little bit
on top of each other so we just simply select
all of them here all the the weird ones from 307
up to 3 11 312 here and we reposition them just
a little bit and this is basically what the layout
view is really good at so let's just do that again
and make sure that we selected all of them like
this and then we go into the move tool here and
we simply drag them a little bit back and now
we have them all separated so now we can work a
little bit better with them so let's select all of
them and let's go down into our controls down here
and they have a width of 50 pixels and a height
of 50 pixels let's just increase that a little bit
to make them a little bit more visible like we
want them like this maybe 80 and 80. maybe that's
fine and then we can certainly much better grab
them and move them around the way we want it so
the layout is basically just a starting point when
we import it from 3d and then we can rearrange it
a little bit like we like we just did here
so let's just uh once again move them into
this one and then i'm going to do the rest of
the fixtures right here and then we're going to
go into the next step afterwards so this one this
time i'm going to speed up the video once again
and i'm going to do all the other other views
for the other fixtures and then when we have done
that we can go and proceed to the next step if you
think you have learned something so far be sure to
give this video a like to give some free support
to my channel i really appreciate it and it really
helps the youtube algorithm to push my video out
to more people and you're also very welcome to
subscribe to the channel i try to upload a video
a new video every week so if you want to continue
learning GrandMA3 this is a good place to be
so subscribe and hit that bell notification
so you don't miss any future uploads another cool
thing we can do after we've done all these layout
windows is to give each fixture type its own color
so if we go into the atomics into the edit again
we can scroll all the way down i've tried
it with the with some of the the different
appearances and it doesn't seem to work for me
i think it's a some kind of bug right now in
the software i hope it's going to be better but i
find kind of a work around is to color the border
and as you can see on all the atomics here all
the borders are hidden but we can simply mark
them all the way down and say visible and then
we can scroll down to border color right here
and then we can mark them once again and we can
choose a border color for our atomic fixtures
so let's just make a kind of a cyan border
color right here close this one down and if
we clear out you can see they are all in a cyan
color once again i'm going to do this to all of
the other fixtures so we can have them each
and and everyone can have their same color
so now i colored all the different fixtures they
all have the same color so you can much better
differentiate one from the other i can see there's
some similar colors over here but never mind the
last thing i'm going to show you in this tutorial
is to be a little bit more specific about what is
in each window because you can actually draw
a large border around a fixture collection as
i'm going to show you right now like this one i
have this selected and i can right click on it
and go into the setup menu if i can hit the
controls and then we can rename it this is
another element we can say custom text we can
say all two lights like this and as you can see
the text come up here in the center and it's very
small so we can set the default font size to 32
and we can set the text vertical up to the top
and that makes it a lot easier when we go into
a setup or into a layout view to see what's
actually in it so if we for instance go into
let's say all our atomics and let's just say for
the fun of it that these ones are on the floor
we can simply choose this plus icon up here
and we can draw a border around these atomics
only and then we can right click and it can be a
little bit hard to hit we can right click and say
floor atomics like this and you can it's
very hard to see but there's a small name
right here in the in the center so we can set the
default font size to 32 for instance and we can
place the text all the way to the top and then we
can simply align this this border just a little
bit oh i need to change this up a little bit
delete these ones and then i can just go up with
the with the this border like this so basically
now if we go out of the setup menu you will have
this one marked out as the flow atomics and then
you know everything else is in the in the roof or
in the trusses i release a new video every week
on this channel so be sure to subscribe and click
the little bell icon if you want to be notified
when i release new content if you are interested
in GrandMA3 be sure to watch this next video
you can see on the screen right now where i will
go through even more GrandMA3 features on our
quest to learn GrandMA3 programming i hope
to see you on the channel again in the future
and until then happy GrandMA3 programming - BYE! :-)